"Don't talk to strangers."
"لا تتكلم مع الغرباء"
You have heard that phrase uttered
لقد سمعتم هذه العبارة لعقود من
by your friends, family, schools and the media for decades.
أصدقائكم, وعائلاتكم, وفي المدرسة و وسائل الإعلام.
It's a norm. It's a social norm.
إنها قول مأثور. إنها قاعدة إجتماعية.
But it's a special kind of social norm,
لكنها نوعية خاصة من القواعد الإجتماعية,
because it's a social norm that wants to tell us
لأنها قاعدة إجتماعية تريد أن تخبرنا
who we can relate to and who we shouldn't relate to.
بمن نستطيع أن نألفه ومن لا يجب أن نألفه.
"Don't talk to strangers" says,
عبارة" لا تتحدث للغرباء" تخبرنا,
"Stay from anyone who's not familiar to you.
بـ"أن نبقى بعيدا عن هؤلاء من ليسوا مثلنا
Stick with the people you know.
وأن نلزم هؤلاء من نعرفهم.
Stick with people like you."
"تلزم من يشبهونك."
How appealing is that?
يا له من شيء جذاب
It's not really what we do, is it, when we're at our best?
انه ليس حقاً ما نقوم به, هل هو كذلك عندما نكون في أفضل حال لنا؟
When we're at our best, we reach out to people
فعندما نكون في أفضل حالاتنا, نرغب في التواصل مع الناس
who are not like us,
الذين لا يشبهوننا,
because when we do that, we learn from people
لأنه عندما نقوم بذلك, نتعلم من الناس
who are not like us.
الذين يختلفون عنا
My phrase for this value of being with "not like us"
صياغتي التي تتضمن قيمة أن نكون مع "من ليسوا مثلنا"
is "strangeness,"
هي "الغرابة,"
and my point is that in today's digitally intensive world,
ومقصدي من هذا هو أن في هذا العالم شديد الرقمية,
strangers are quite frankly not the point.
الغرباء ليسوا هم المقصودون تماما.
The point that we should be worried about is,
الغرض هو أن ما يجب أن نقلق حياله هو,
how much strangeness are we getting?
ما قدر الغرابة التي نتلقاها؟
Why strangeness? Because our social relations
لم الغرابة؟ لأن روابطنا الإجتماعية
are increasingly mediated by data,
تتوسطها البيانات بشكل متزايد,
and data turns our social relations into digital relations,
والبيانات تحول روابطنا الإجتماعية إلى روابط رقمية,
and that means that our digital relations
وهذا يعني أن روابطنا الرقمية
now depend extraordinarily on technology
تعتمد الآن على التقنية بشكل فائق
to bring to them a sense of robustness,
لتجلب لهم الإحساس بالقوة,
a sense of discovery,
الإحساس بالإكتشاف,
a sense of surprise and unpredictability.
الإحساس بالمفاجأة و بالغير متوقع.
Why not strangers?
فلم لا يكون الإحساس بالغرباء أيضا؟
Because strangers are part of a world
لأن الغرباء جزء من
of really rigid boundaries.
العالم ذا الفواصل المتصلبة
They belong to a world of people I know
ينتمون لعالم فيه أناس أعرفهم
versus people I don't know,
مقابل أناس لا أعرفهم,
and in the context of my digital relations,
وفي سياق روابطي الرقمية,
I'm already doing things with people I don't know.
أنا بالفعل أقوم بأشياء مع أناس لا أعرفهم.
The question isn't whether or not I know you.
السؤال ليس إذا كنت أعرفك أم لا.
The question is, what can I do with you?
السؤال هو, ما الذي يمكنني أن أقوم به معك؟
What can I learn with you?
ما الذي يمكنني تعلمه معك؟
What can we do together that benefits us both?
ما الذي يمكننا أن نقوم به سويا لنستفيد؟
I spend a lot of time thinking about
أقضي وقتا كبيرا أفكر في
how the social landscape is changing,
الكيفية التي يتغير به الشكل الإجتماعي,
how new technologies create new constraints
وكيف أن التقنيات تخلق قيودا جديدة
and new opportunities for people.
وفرصا جديدة للناس.
The most important changes facing us today
التغييرات الأكثر أهمية اتي تواجهنا هذا الأيام
have to do with data and what data is doing
لها علاقة بالبيانات والتي بدورها تقوم
to shape the kinds of digital relations
بتشكيل أنواع الروابط الرقمية
that will be possible for us in the future.
التي ستكون ممكنة لنا في المستقبل.
The economies of the future depend on that.
إقتصاديات المستقبل تعتمد على ذلك.
Our social lives in the future depend on that.
حيواتنا الإجتماعية تعتمد على ذلك في المستقبل.
The threat to worry about isn't strangers.
التهديد المقلق ليس الغرباء.
The threat to worry about is whether or not
التهديد هو هل نحصل أم لا
we're getting our fair share of strangeness.
على حصتنا من الغرابة.
Now, 20th-century psychologists and sociologists
الآن, أخصائيو علم النفس و الإجتماع في القرن العشرين
were thinking about strangers,
كانوا يفكرون أن الغرباء
but they weren't thinking so dynamically about human relations,
ولكنهم لم يكونوا يفكرون بتفاعلية الروابط الإجتماعية كما يجب
and they were thinking about strangers
وكانوا يفكرون عن الغرباء
in the context of influencing practices.
في سياق الممارسات المؤثرة.
Stanley Milgram from the '60s and '70s,
ستينلي ميلجرام من الـ60 والـ70,
the creator of the small-world experiments,
صاحب تجارب العالم الصغير
which became later popularized as six degrees of separation,
والذي أُشتهر فيما بعد بالست درجات الفاصلة,
made the point that any two arbitrarily selected people
قدم لنا أن أي شخصين إعتباطيين
were likely connected from between five to seven intermediary steps.
من المرجح أنهما يتصلا فيما بين خمس أو سبع خطوات.
His point was that strangers are out there.
طرحه هو أن الغرباء في العالم
We can reach them. There are paths
يمكننا أن نتواصل معهم. فهناك دروب
that enable us to reach them.
تمكننا من الوصول اليهم.
Mark Granovetter, Stanford sociologist, in 1973
قال مارك جرانوڨيتر, أخصائي علم الإجتماع في عام 1973
in his seminal essay "The Strength of Weak Ties,"
في بحثه الممتد "قوة الروابط الضعيفة,"
made the point that these weak ties
يشير إلى أن تلك الروابط الضعيفة
that are a part of our networks, these strangers,
والتي هي جزء من شبكات علاقاتنا, وهؤلاء الغرباء
are actually more effective at diffusing information to us
في الواقع هم أكثر قدرة على تعطيل وصول المعلومات إلينا
than are our strong ties, the people closest to us.
من هؤلاء من تربطنا بهم روابط قوية, المقربون لنا.
He makes an additional indictment of our strong ties
و يتهم روابطنا القوية باتهام إضافي
when he says that these people who are so close to us,
عندما يقول أن المقربون لنا,
these strong ties in our lives,
لديهم روبط قوية بنا,
actually have a homogenizing effect on us.
في الواقع لديهم تأثير متجانس علينا.
They produce sameness.
يتسببون في حالة من التشابه,
My colleagues and I at Intel have spent the last few years
مضيت مع زملائي في شركة إنتل الأعوام الماضية
looking at the ways in which digital platforms
نبحث عن طرق تشكل من خلالها المنصات الرقمية
are reshaping our everyday lives,
حيواتنا كل يوم,
what kinds of new routines are possible.
ما أنواع طرز الحياة الممكنة.
We've been looking specifically at the kinds
كنا نبحث تحديدا في تلك الأنواع
of digital platforms that have enabled us
من المنصات الرقمية التي مكنتنا
to take our possessions, those things that used to be
من أخذ ممتلكاتنا, تلك الأشياء التي إعتادت أن تكون
very restricted to us and to our friends in our houses,
مقصورة علينا فقط, نحن وأصدقائنا في بيوتنا,
and to make them available to people we don't know.
و أن نجعلها متاحة لأناس لا نعرفهم.
Whether it's our clothes, whether it's our cars,
سواء كانت هذه الأشياء ملابسنا, أو سياراتنا,
whether it's our bikes, whether it's our books or music,
أو دراجاتنا, أو كتبنا أو موسيقانا
we are able to take our possessions now
في مقدورنا أن نأخذ ممتلكاتنا الآن
and make them available to people we've never met.
ونجعلها متاحة لأناس لم نقابلهم قط.
And we concluded a very important insight,
وقد خلصنا إلى نتيجة مهمة,
which was that as people's relationships
حيث أن كما علاقات الناس
to the things in their lives change,
بالأشياء التي في حياتها تتغير,
so do their relations with other people.
كذلك العلاقات بين الناس.
And yet recommendation system
ولا زال نظام ترجيح
after recommendation system continues to miss the boat.
تلو الآخر, يستمر في التماشي مع الواقع.
It continues to try to predict what I need
يستمر في محاولته لتوقع ما أحتاجه
based on some past characterization of who I am,
إعتمادا على خصائص من الماضي حول الشخص الذي كنته,
of what I've already done.
لما قمت به بالفعل.
Security technology after security technology
تقنية أمنية تلو الأخرى
continues to design data protection
تستمر في تصميم نظام حماية للبيانات
in terms of threats and attacks,
متعلق بالتهديدات و الإعتداءات,
keeping me locked into really rigid kinds of relations.
تبقيني رهينة أنواع جامدة من العلاقات.
Categories like "friends" and "family"
تصنيفات كـ "أصدقاء" و "عائلة"
and "contacts" and "colleagues"
و "وسائل الإتصال" و "زملاء"
don't tell me anything about my actual relations.
لا تخبرني بأي شيء عن علاقاتي الواقعية,
A more effective way to think about my relations
طريقة أكثر كفائة للتفكير بعلاقاتي
might be in terms of closeness and distance,
ربمل تكون فيما يتعلق بالدنو و البعد,
where at any given point in time, with any single person,
اين أنا في نقطة معينة من الزمن بالنسبة لشخص واحد,
I am both close and distant from that individual,
أكون قريبا وبعيدا من ذلك الشخص,
all as a function of what I need to do right now.
الأمر كله عائد إلى ما أحتاجه في هذه اللحظة.
People aren't close or distant.
الناس ليسوا قريبين أو بعيدين.
People are always a combination of the two,
الناس دائما خليط بين الإثنين,
and that combination is constantly changing.
و هذا الخليط دائم التغيير.
What if technologies could intervene
فماذا لو تدخلت التقنية
to disrupt the balance of certain kinds of relationships?
لإحدث خلل في توازن أنواع معينة من العلاقات؟
to help me find the person that I need right now?
لمساعدتي في الوصول للشخص الذي أحتاجه الآن؟
Strangeness is that calibration
الغرابة هي معايرة
of closeness and distance
لـلدنو و البعد
that enables me to find the people that I need right now,
و هذا يمكنني من الوصول للناس التي أحتاجها الآن,
that enables me to find the sources of intimacy,
ويمكنني من الحصول على مصدر للحميمية,
of discovery, and of inspiration that I need right now.
وللإكتشاف, وللإلهام أنا في حاجة له الآن.
Strangeness is not about meeting strangers.
الغرابة ليست مقابلة الغرباء.
It simply makes the point that we need
إنها ببساطة تحقق لنا ما نريد
to disrupt our zones of familiarity.
لإحداث خلل في محيطنا المألوف.
So jogging those zones of familiarity is one way to think about strangeness,
فهز تلك المناطق المألوفة هي طريقة للتفكير حول الغرابة,
and it's a problem faced not just by individuals today,
وهي مشكلة تتحدى ليس فقط الأفراد اليوم
but also by organizations,
ولكن تتحدى المنظمات أيضا,
organizations that are trying to embrace massively new opportunities.
منظمات تحاول إستثمار كل فرصة جديدة بشكل هائل.
Whether you're a political party
سواء كنت حزبا سياسيا
insisting to your detriment on a very rigid notion
مصرا على مضرة نظرية متجمدة..
of who belongs and who does not,
لمن ينتمي و من لا ينتمي,
whether you're the government
سواء كنت الحكومة
protecting social institutions like marriage
تقوم بحماية هيئات اجتماعية كالزواج
and restricting access of those institutions to the few,
ومقيدا هيئات كهذه لفئة قليلة,
whether you're a teenager in her bedroom
سواء كنت مراهقة في مخدعها
who's trying to jostle her relations with her parents,
تحاول الصدام مع والديها,
strangeness is a way to think about how we pave the way
الغرابة هي طريقة تفكير لتمهيد الطريق
to new kinds of relations.
لأنواع جديدة من العلاقات
We have to change the norms.
يجب أن نغير ما هو طبيعي
We have to change the norms in order to enable
يجب أن نغير ما هو مألوف لكي نمكن
new kinds of technologies
أنواع جديدة من التقنيات
as a basis for new kinds of businesses.
كأساس لأنواع جدية من الأعمال.
What interesting questions lie ahead for us
ما الأسئلة المشوقة التي تنتظرنا في المستقبل
in this world of no strangers?
في هذا العالم الذي بلا غرباء؟
How might we think differently about our relations with people?
كيف يمكن التفكير حول علاقاتنا بالناس بشكل مختلف؟
How might we think differently about our relations
كيف يمكننا التفكير بشكل مختلف حول علاقاتنا
with distributed groups of people?
بمجموعات متفرقة من الناس؟
How might we think differently about our relations with technologies,
كيف يمكننا أن نفكر بشكل ختلف حول علاقاتنا بالتقنية,
things that effectively become social participants
أشياء تصبح مشاركة إجتماعيا بشكل فاعل
in their own right?
بما يناسبها؟
The range of digital relations is extraordinary.
نطاق العلاقات الرقمية هائل
In the context of this broad range of digital relations,
وفي سياق هذا النطاق العريض من العلاقات الرقمية,
safely seeking strangeness might very well be
البحث عن الغرابة بشكل آمن قد يكون وبشكل حسن
a new basis for that innovation.
أساس جديد لذلك الإبتكار
Thank you.
أشكركم
(Applause)
(تصفيق)